the loss of the Wonderful Wizard, and would not be comforted end of Chapter 17
this is a librivox recording all librivox recordings are in the public
domain for more information or to volunteer please visit librivox.org this recording by jay hall
The Wonderful Wizard of Oz by l frank Baum Chapter 18 Away to the South
Dorothy wept bitterly at the passing of her hope to get home to Kansas again; but
when she thought it all over she was glad she had not gone up in a balloon.
And she also felt sorry at losing Oz, and so did her companions. The Tin Woodman
came to her and said: “Truly I should be ungrateful if I fail to mourn for a man
who gave me a lovely heart. I should like to cry a little because Oz is gone, if
you will kindly wipe away my tears, so that I shall not rust.” “With pleasure,” she
answered, and brought a towel at once.
Then the Tin Woodman wept for several minutes, and she watched the tears
carefully and wiped them away with the towel. When he had finished, he thanked
her kindly and oiled himself thoroughly with his jeweled oil can to guard
against mishap. The Scarecrow was now the ruler of the Emerald City, and although
he was not a Wizard the people were proud of him. “For,” they said, “there is not
another city in all the world that is ruled by a stuffed man.” And, so far as
they knew, they were quite right. The morning after the balloon had gone up
with Oz, the four travelers met in the Throne Room and talked matters over. The
Scarecrow sat in the big throne and the other stood respectfully before him. “We
are not so unlucky,” said the new ruler, “for this Palace in the Emerald City
belonged to us, and we can do just as we please.
When I remember that a short time ago I
was up on a pole in a farmer’s cornfield,
and that now I am the ruler of this beautiful City, I am quite satisfied with
my lot.” “I also,” said the Tin Woodman and well pleased with my new heart; and,
really, that was the only thing I wished in all the world.” “For my part, I am
content and knowing I am as brave as any beast that ever lived, if not braver,” said
the Lion modestly. “If Dorothy would only be content to live in the Emerald City,” continued
the Scarecrow, “we might all be happy together.” “But I don’t want to live here,”
cried Dorothy. “I want to go to Kansas, and live with Aunt Em and Uncle Henry.” “Well,
then, what can be done?” inquired the Woodman. The Scarecrow decided to think,
and he thought so hard that the pins and needles began to stick out of his brains.
Finally he said: “Why not called the Winged Monkeys, and asked them to carry
you over the desert?” “I never thought of that it said Dorothy joyfully. “It’s just the thing.
I’ll go at once for the Golden Cap.” When she brought it into the Throne Room she
spoke the magic words, and soon the band of Winged Monkeys flew in through the
open window and stood beside her. “This is the second time you have called us,” said
the Monkey King, bowing before the little girl. “What do you wish?” “I want you to fly
with me to Kansas,” said Dorothy. But the Monkey King shook his head this cannot
be done,” he said. “We belong to this country alone, and cannot leave it. There
has never been a Winged Monkey in Kansas yet, and I suppose there never will be,
for they don’t belong there. We should be glad to serve you in any way in our
power, but we cannot cross the desert goodbye And with another bow, the Monkey
King spread his wings and flew away through the window, followed by all his
band. Dorothy was ready to cry with disappointment. “I have wasted the charm
of the Golden Cap to no purpose,” she said, “for the Winged Monkeys cannot help me.” “It
is certainly too bad!” said the tender-hearted Woodman. The Scarecrow was
thinking again, and his head bulged out so horribly that Dorothy feared it would burst.
“Let us call in the soldier with the green whiskers,” he said, “and ask his
advice.” So the soldier was summoned and entered the Throne Room timidly, for
while Oz was alive he never was allowed to come farther than the door. “This
little girl,” said the Scarecrow to the soldier, “wishes to cross the desert.
How can she do so?” “I cannot tell,” answered the soldier, “for no one has ever crossed
the desert, unless it is Oz himself.” “Is there no one who will help me?” asked
Dorothy earnestly. “Glinda might,” he suggested.
“Who is Glenda inquired the Scarecrow. “The Witch of the South. She is the most
powerful of all the Witches, and rules over the Quadlings. Besides, her castle
stands on the edge of the desert, so she
may know a way to cross it.” “Glinda is a
Good Witch, isn’t she?” asked the child. “The Quadlings thinks she is good,” said the
soldier, “and she is kind everyone. I have heard that Glinda is a beautiful woman,
who knows how to keep young in spite of the many years she has lived.” “How can I
get to her castle?” asked Dorothy. “The road is straight to the South,” he answered, “but
is said to be full of dangers to travelers. There are wild beasts in the
woods, and a race of queer men who do not like strangers to cross their country.
For this reason none of the Quadlings ever come to the Emerald City.” The
soldier then left them and the Scarecrow said: “It seems, in spite of dangers, that
the best thing Dorothy can do is travel to the Land of the South and ask Glinda
to help her. For, of course, if Dorothy stays here she will never get back to
Kansas.” “You must have been thinking again,” remarked the Tin Woodman. “I have,” said the
Scarecrow. “I shall go with Dorothy,” declared the Lion, “for I am tired of your
city and long for the woods in the country again. I am really a wild beast, you know.
Besides, Dorothy will need someone to protect her.” “That is true,” agreed the
Woodman. “My axe may be of service to her;
so I shall go with her to the Land of the South.” “When shall we start?” asked the
Scarecrow. “Are you going?” they asked, in surprise. “Certainly. If it wasn’t for
Dorothy I should never have had brains.
She lifted me from the pole in this cornfield and brought me to the Emerald City.
So my good luck is all due to her, and I shall never leave her until she starts
back to Kansas for good and all.” “Thank you,” said Dorothy gratefully. “You are all
very kind to me. But I should like to start as soon as possible.” “We shall go
tomorrow morning,” returned the Scarecrow.
“So now let us all get ready, for it will